<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act declaring the grounds and causes of making prize the ships and goods that shall be taken from time to time by the Parliaments ships at sea, and for the encouragement of officers, mariners and seamen. Die Martis, 17 April, 1649. Ordered by the Commons assembled in Parliament, that this act be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliament'.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1060_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867521</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867521</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119836</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119836)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 157:E1060[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act declaring the grounds and causes of making prize the ships and goods that shall be taken from time to time by the Parliaments ships at sea, and for the encouragement of officers, mariners and seamen. Die Martis, 17 April, 1649. Ordered by the Commons assembled in Parliament, that this act be forthwith printed and published. Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliament'.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 157-169 [i.e. 20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Edward Husband, printer to the Honorable House of Commons, and are to be sold at his shop in Fleetstreet, at the sign of the Golden-Dragon, near the Inner-Temple,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>April 20. 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On 2E2: the last word of first line of text: 'Parliament' (roman); first word of line below initial: 'forbidden'; last word of last full line of text: 'Inhabi-'.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of a through-paged folio set with a table for the entire set added.</note>
                  <note>Title ornament; initial letter; text in black letter.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: 2E⁴ 2F⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prize law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119836:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACT Declaring the Grounds and Cauſes of making PRIZE THE SHIPS and GOODS that ſhall be taken from time to time by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Ships at Sea, and for the encouragement of Officers, Mariners and Seamen.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the Commonwealth of England</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>Die Martis, 17 April, 1649.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That this Act be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliament'.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Huſband,</hi> Printer to the Honorable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and are to be ſold at his Shop in Fleetſtreet, at the Sign of the Golden-Dragon, near the Inner-Temple, <hi>April</hi> 20. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:119836:2"/>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:119836:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT Declaring the Grounds and Cauſes of making Prize the Ships and Goods, that ſhall be taken from time to time by the Parliament Ships at Sea, and for the encouragement of Officers, Marriners and Seamen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHereas the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by ſeveral Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Acts made and promulged, for the neceſſary Defence of the Dominions and Common-Wealth of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of Reaſon and Nations, forbidden Commerce and Trade to any ports or places within thoſe Nations, being in rebellion and hoſtility againſt the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> and more particularly by an Ordinance dated the 30 of <hi>November,</hi> 1643. power was given to ſeize and ſurprize all and all maner of Ships and Veſſels, with the Ordnance, Ammunition, Victuals, Goods, Commanders and Soldiers therein, that ſhould be met withal in or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, bound from any Port or place within the Dominions of theſe Nations, being in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament, or coming from, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to any ſuch Port or place; or that ſhould be found to have Traded with the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:119836:3"/> of any ſuch port or place ſince their defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the Parliament, and alſo to ſeize, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and take all Ships, Veſſels, Ordnance, Ammunition, Victuals and Goods belonging to and Rebel or Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all maner of Pirats and Sea-Rovers, of what Nation ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and their Ships and Goods, and the ſame to procure to be adjudged in the High-Court of Admiralty for lawful prize; And by another Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the 29 of <hi>January,</hi> 1645. power was given for the ſetting forth ſhips to Sea, equip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, furniſhed and armed, in Warlike maner, and the ſame to employ for the ſeizing, taking, and ſurprizing of all ſhips and veſſels belonging to any of the ſubjects of theſe Dominions, which ſhould be met withal in or outwards, bound from any port or place, being in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament; together with all the Ordnance, Ammunition, Victuals, Goods, Commanders and Soldiers therein; as alſo for the ſeizing, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing and taking of all Ships and Veſſels whatſoever, with the Ordnance, Ammunition, Victuals and Goods therein, belonging to any Rebel or Rebels in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and alſo the ſhips and goods of any other perſon whatſoever, Foreigner or other, which ſhall be going to, or coming from any port or place in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament; as alſo for the ſeizing, ſurprizing and taking of all and all maner of ſhips and veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels belonging to any Foreigner, or of any Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Nation going to any port or place in Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity againſt the Parliament, with Arms, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, or other Contrabanda goods, for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the Forces raiſed againſt the Parliament, and adjudging and condemning the ſame, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the goods themſelves, and all ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goods as belong to the Maſters or Laders
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:119836:3"/> of ſuch Contrabanda goods; and likewiſe for the ſeizing, ſurprizing and taking all Pirats and Sea-Rovers, of what Nation ſoever, and their ſhips and goods whatſoever, according to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, meaning and true intent of the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the ſaid 30 of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1643. and by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Ordinance printed <hi>April</hi> 6. 1644. power was given for the equipping, arming and ſetting forth ſhips to Sea, to ſeize, ſurprize and take all ſhips and veſſels, with the Ordnance, Ammunition, Goods, Commanders and Soldiers therein, that they ſhould finde were ſent, or to come to any parts of this Nation, to the prejudice thereof: And further likewiſe Ordained, That there ſhould be true and faithful Inventories taken of the Ships, Ammunition, Moneys, Goods, Plate, Pillage and Spoil which ſhould be taken, and a true appraiſment made of the ſame; and the ſame, together with all papers and writings found in any ſhips or other veſſels ſo taken, to be carefully preſerved, and two or three of the Officers of every ſhip or veſſel ſo taken, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be brought up and examined in the Court of Admiralty, concerning the property of the ſaid ſhips and goods, and ſuch other Queſtions and Interrogatories as ſhould be thought fit to be adminiſtred unto them; or otherwiſe, that the ſaid Officers of the ſaid ſhips or veſſels ſo taken, ſhould be examined before the chief Officer of the next port of <hi>England;</hi> and the ſaid Examinations, with the ſaid papers, inventories &amp; apprizements, to be ſent unto the Regiſter of the High Court of Admiralty aforeſaid, to the end that thereby, and by ſuch other proofs and evidences as ſhould be produced in the ſaid Court, the taking and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing of the ſaid ſhips, veſſels and goods might be juſtified, and ſentence of condemnation be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulged;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:119836:4"/> or otherwiſe, if there ſhould be found juſt cauſe for reſtitution to the firſt owners or former proprietors, that Iuſtice ſhould be duly adminiſtred, and Reſtitution awarded: And by an Act of this preſent Parliament, made in <hi>February,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred forty eight, Ordered the Two and twentieth of <hi>February</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid to be printed and publiſhed, entituled, <hi>An Act for encouragement of Officers and Mariners, and Impreſting Seamen,</hi> It is Enacted and Ordain-amongſt other things, That if the ſhip or ſhips employed in the ſervice of the Parliament, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in that Act, ſhould take or ſurprize any of the Revolted ſhips, that then they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded as in that Act is contained: And alſo in caſe they ſhould ſurprize or take any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhips, Engliſh or Stranger, declaring himſelf againſt the Parliament, or carrying any Ordnance, Ammunition, Corn or any other proviſions, to aſsiſt againſt the Parliament, that the ſhip and goods ſo taken before they break bulk, ſhall firſt be adjudged in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty Court, with divers other clauſes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, as well in the ſaid laſt mentioned Act, as in the ſaid former Ordinances, and other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances contained: The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> conceiving it requiſite, as well for the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Marriners and Seamen, and well-affected, the better to perform their duties, as for the taking away of all excuſe from ſuch as ſhall hereafter offend, and be found culpable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the making and publiſhing of this Act, That therefore, and for divers other weighty reaſons, there ſhould out of all the ſaid former Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Acts, and ſuch other ſupplements as ſhould be neceſſary for the guard of the Narrow Seas, proeection and preſervation of Trade,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:119836:4"/> and neceſſary defence and ſafeguard of theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Commonwealth, be one entire Law and Act of Parliament, framed, made, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed, according to the Law of Nations, manifeſting and reciting therein entirely toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they may be readily diſcerned at one view, the ſeveral and particular caſes, which they for their neceſſary preſervation, and other the weighty reaſons aforeſaid, do Declare and Ordain to be juſt cauſes of ſeizure and adjudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for lawful prize, together alſo with the other clauſes and regulations hereafter in this Act ſet forth: It is therefore Eſtabliſhed, Ordained and Enacted, and be it Enacted by this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and by the authority of the ſame, That it ſhall and may be lawful, as well for any of the Parliament ſhips, or other ſhips or veſſels what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſet out or to be ſet out or employed by them in their ſervice, as alſo for any other ſhips, veſſels, or private Men of War, approved or to be approved thereto, by the immediate authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Parliament, or by the Councel of State eſtabliſhed by Parliament, to ſeize, ſurprize, and take, not onely all and every the Revolted ſhipes that have treacherouſly betrayed their Truſt, and made defection from the Parliament; but alſo all ſuch other ſhips or veſſels whatſoever, and all the Ordnance, Ammunition, Proviſions, Victuals, Wares, Merchandizes and Goods whatſoever in the ſame ſhips or veſſels, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any Foreigner or other perſon whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that have or ſhall aſſociate or joyn with the revolted ſhips, or any of them, or carry them any Arms, Ammunition, Victuals or Proviſions, or ſhall yield them any aſsiſtance againſt the Parliament; and alſo all other ſhips and veſſels whatſoever, of this or any Foreign Nation
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:119836:5"/> whatſoever (with all the Ordnance, Ammunition Proviſions and Goods whatſoever, therein to be found) which ſhal accept, receive or take any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion or Commiſsions, or Letters of Marque, or other authority from or under <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> ſon to the late deceaſed King of <hi>England,</hi> or any other Son of the ſaid late deceaſed King, or from or under Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> calling himſelf <hi>Prince Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi> and alſo all the ſhips, veſſels and goods, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and Soldiers of the ſaid <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> Son to the ſaid late deceaſed King, and of the ſaid Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> and both and either of them: And alſo all other ſhips and veſſels, with the Ordnance, Ammunition, Victuals, Proviſions, Goods, Wares and Merchandizes whatſoever (of any of the people of theſe Nations, or any Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Nation whatſoever) therein carrying any maner of Contrabanda goods, that ſhall be met withal in any port or place, or inwards or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, bound from any port or place within the Dominions of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or that then ſhall be in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament, or that ſhall be found Trading, or within the ſpace of ſix moneths before the ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure, to have Traded in the time of their defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within any ſuch port or place aforeſaid, being as aforeſaid in Defection or Hoſtility againſt the Parliament: And alſo all the Ships, Veſſels, Arms, Ammunition and Goods whatſoever, of any perſons Foreigners, of what Foreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever, or other perſons whatſoever, which ſhall be going to any port or place, then being in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament, with Soldiers or Arms, Ammunition or other Contrabanda goods, for ſupply or aſsiſtance of any Forces raiſed or to be raiſed againſt the Parliament, or which ſhall be deſigned, ſent or ordered to carry,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:119836:5"/> tranſport or bring any Commanders, Soldiers, Forces, Arms or Ammunition into <hi>England,</hi> to the diſturbance of the Peace, or prejudice thereof; and alſo all the ſhips, veſſels, proviſions and goods of what kinde ſoever, belonging to any Rebel or Rebels in <hi>Ireland:</hi> All which, and every of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars aforeſaid, ſhall be, and ſhall in the High Court of Admiralty of <hi>England,</hi> upon due proof, and according to legal courſe in that caſe, be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged and condemned for lawful prize. And for that <hi>Ireland</hi> hath of long time been, and ſtill is, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant of <hi>England,</hi> and ſubject to ſuch Laws, Orders, Regulements and Conſtitutions as are or ſhall be made by the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> and for that not onely divers provinces, ports and places in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but even the province of <hi>Munſter</hi> it ſelf, with all the ports and places under the command of the Lord <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> have lately trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly betrayed the truſt repoſed in them by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and made defection, and Rebelled, and are <hi>in rei veritate,</hi> and ſo by the Laws of Nations ought to be accompted to be notorious Rebels, that ought not to hold any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of correſpondency abroad, nor to enjoy the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of commerce or traffique: And for that the Parliament doth ſpeedily intend, by the aſſiſtance of God, to uſe all lawful and juſt means for their ſuppreſſion, and puniſhment of their ſaid Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reduction of all thoſe ports, provinces and places in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to fidelity and due obedience; and for the Reaſons aforeſaid doth declare and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, That they prohibite and forbid all maner of Commerce, Traffique and correſpondency what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, to be uſed or held with any of the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or within any of the Provinces, Ports, Harbors, Rivers or places of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the poſſeſsion, or under the power of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels to the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> Be it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:119836:6"/> further Enacted by this preſent Parliament, and by the authority of the ſame, that it ſhall and may be lawful, to any of the Fleet or ſhips ſet forth or to be ſet forth or imployed by or under the Parliament, or any private Men of War, or ſhips to be allowed or approved by the immediate pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Parliament, or the Councel of State eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Parliament, To ſeize, ſurprize &amp; take all and all maner of ſhips, veſſels and goods, of what nature or kinde ſoever, belonging to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, whether Foreign or other, which ſhall be found or met withal in any Port, Harbor, Creek, River or place in <hi>Ireland,</hi> being in the poſſeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Rebels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any of them, or under their power and command, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in hoſtility againſt the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> and alſo all ſhips, veſſels and goods, of what Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever, that ſhal be going to, or coming from any ſuch port, harbor or place in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands or poſſeſſion of the ſaid Rebels, or any of them, or in hoſtility againſt the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> as aforeſaid. And be it likewiſe Enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforeſaid, That whatſoever prize or prizes ſhall be ſo ſeized, ſurprized or taken in all or any of the caſes aforeſaid, by vertue of this Act, ſhall be ſafely preſerved and kept, without pillaging, ſpoiling, imbezling, or in any ſort breaking of bulk, until after judgement ſhall be given concerning the ſame in the High Court of Admiralty of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And that no Captain, or any other officers or Mariners that ſhall ſo take ſuch prize or prizes, ſhall break bulk, nor imbezle, nor ſuffer to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezled, purloined, taken or ſtoln away, any of the Tackles, Apparel, Furniture or Goods, of or in any of the ſaid ſhips or veſſels ſo taken as prize, but ſhall cauſe the ſame entire to be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome Engliſh Port, where the ſame ſhall be ſecured by the chief Magiſtrate of that Port, or
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:119836:6"/> ſuch as he ſhal imploy for that purpoſe, with ſome two or more ſuch perſons to look thereunto, as the Officers and Mariners intereſſed ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt, until the ſame ſhall be viewed, inventoried, apprized and further ſecured, by ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as ſhall be appointed thereunto by the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of State,</hi> on the one part, and the perſons truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as aforeſaid, in behalf of the Officers, Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Seamen intereſſed, on the other part; and until Iudgement ſhall be given in the ſaid Court of Admiralty, upon &amp; concerning the ſaid reſpective ſhips and goods ſo taken as aforeſaid in due courſe of Law. And to the end that there may be a fair, legal and juſt proceeding in the ſaid Court of Admiralty, upon &amp; concerning all and ſingular the ſaid premiſes, in all and every the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes aforeſaid, Be it Enacted by the authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, That all and every the charter, parties, cockets, bills of lading, Commiſſions, Letters of Mart, private Letters, Inſtruments, Contracts and all other documents and writings whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that ſhall be taken or found in every and any of the ſaid ſhips or veſſels ſo to be taken or ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by vertue of this Act, or found upon any of the perſons in the ſame, ſhall be duly and ſafely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and ſent up or tranſmitted into the ſaid Court of Admiralty. And that alſo two or three of the officers or principal perſons of, or found in every ſuch ſhip or veſſel ſo taken as aforeſaid, ſhal either be brought up or ſent to be examined upon oath in the ſaid Court of Admiralty, as wel tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſaid writings found in the ſaid ſhip or veſſel, and the proprietors, owners and maſters of the ſame ſhips, and the goods therein, and the places from whence they came, and whether they were bound, &amp; ſuch other queſtions &amp; interogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as in each particular caſe ſhalbe found meet to be adminiſtred unto them; or otherwiſe in caſe they cannot be conveniently ſent up to the ſaid Court,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:119836:7"/> That then the ſaid Officers, and two, three, or more of the principal men ſo taken or found in the ſaid ſhips or veſſels, ſhall be duly examined upon Oath, before the chief Officer of ſome port in <hi>England,</hi> or ſome Iuſtice of the Peace, of and concerning the matters, particulars and premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes before recited: And as well all and every their ſuch Examinations, as alſo all and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the ſaid Writings found aboard the ſaid ſhips, ſhall be duly tranſmitted and ſent in to the ſaid Court of Admiralty. And it is further Enacted, That the Iudges of the ſaid Court of Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, upon peruſal of the ſaid Examinations, and of the ſaid Writings ſo tranſmitted unto them, and ſuch other evidences and proofs as ſhall in due courſe of Law be made or exhibited before them, as well on the one ſide, for proving and juſtifying the ſame to be prize, as for and on the behalf of all other perſons that ſhall in the proceeding of the ſaid cauſes appear, and put in any claims, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the defence for the ſaid ſhips or goods ſo taken, or any of them, ſhal duly proceed to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and upon due and deliberate conſideration of the ſaid proofs on both ſides, and the allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and pleas on either ſide, ſhall in all and every the particulars and caſes declared to be prize by this Act, by definitive ſentence to be promulged in the ſaid Court, adjudge and condemn the ſaid ſhips and goods ſo taken, to be duly taken, and to be good and lawful prize. And where it ſhall upon proof fall out of the particulars and caſes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by this Act as aforeſaid to be prize, there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Iudges ſhal, according to the merits of the caſes, award reſtitution to the owners, maſters or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors, &amp; in all caſes duly adminiſter true juſtice to either party, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true intent &amp; mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Act: <hi>Provided</hi> always, that if any prize or prizes ſo taken, or any part thereof, ſhal appear and be proved in the ſaid Court of Admiralty,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:119836:7"/> to be any ſhip or goods belonging to any of the well-affected and good People of <hi>England</hi> or of <hi>Ireland,</hi> remaining and continuing under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Parliament, and before taken or ſurprized from them by any Enemy or Rebel, or diſaffected perſon, and afterwards again ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized and retaken by any of the Fleet or Ships imployed or to be imployed in the ſervice of the Parliament, or any private Man of War, or other ſhip or veſſel under the protection or obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Parliament, That then ſuch ſhips and goods, and every ſuch part and parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as aforeſaid, belonging to the ſaid good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aforeſaid, ſhall be adjudged to be reſtored, and ſhall be by Decree of the ſaid Court of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty accordingly reſtored to ſuch former owner and owners, or proprietors; paying for and in lieu of ſalvage, onely one eight part of the true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the ſhips and goods reſpectively ſo to be reſtored, unleſs ſuch ſhips ſo retaken, ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have been after their taking by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Rebels or diſaffected, ſet forth by them as Men of War on their behalf: In which caſe the ſaid true and firſt owners and proprietors to whom the ſame ſhall be reſtored, ſhall be adjud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to pay, and ſhall pay for ſalvage the full moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of the true value of the ſaid ſhips ſo retaken and reſtored. And the ſaid Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> doth Declare, That as they do make, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulge and ſet forth this Act for the ſeizing and taking of prizes, in the particular caſes, and upon the juſt and weighty Reaſons aforeſaid, for their neceſſary defence and preſervation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Liberty which the Laws of Nature, Reaſon, and Nations allows them in theſe Caſes, without Infringing or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching upon any the Leagues, Treaties,
<pb facs="tcp:119836:8"/> or Articles of Peace heretofore made between any Forreign Kings, Princes, States or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the ſaid Dominions of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> ſo they do intend to uphold, maintain, and keep, and are ready to renew the Leagues and Amities between theſe and Foreign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Kingdoms and States, and freely to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, ſuffer, and give encouragement to all Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners and Strangers; and all the Subjects of Foreign Nations and Countreys in amity with theſe Nations, to uſe, exerciſe, have and enjoy the full liberty of all maner of Trade and commerce, as well to and with the city of <hi>London,</hi> as alſo to and with all &amp; every the ports and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces within <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſtanding right, and keeping their fidelity to the Parliament, they paying the Cuſtoms, and diſcharging ſuch du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as are rightfully due and accuſtomed. And for the encouragement of Seamen and Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to apply themſelves the more willingly to the ſervice of the Commonwealth; Be it alſo Enacted by the authority aforeſaid, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhip or ſhips of the Parliament, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed immediately under them in this Service, ſhall take, ſurprize or reduce any of the ſaid Revolted ſhips, or any private Man of War, or other Man of War belonging to the ſaid <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> Son to the ſaid late deceaſed King, or the ſaid Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> or that hath or ſhall take or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any Commiſsion from or under them, or either of them, or any other perſon, to fight againſt the Parliament, or diſturb the peace of this Commonwealth, or infeſt the Seas, and hinder the free Trade and Traffiique of Merchants, and other good people by Sea or otherwiſe, ſhall have for reward, over and above their wages, one moyety of the full
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:119836:8"/> value of all and every ſuch Ship or Ships ſurprized or taken as aforeſaid, and of the goods therein taken, to be diſtributed amongſt the Captains, and other Officers and Mariners of the ſaid ſhip or ſhips, according to the Cuſtom of the Sea, Tun for Tun, and Man for Man; and the other moyety ſhall be put into a common Treaſury, for the relief of the Officers and Mariners which ſhall be ſick or wounded, and the Widows, Children and Impotent parents of ſuch as ſhall be ſlain in the ſervice of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth at Sea: The ſettling of which Treaſury in truſty hands, and the ordering thereof for the uſe aforeſaid, is referred to the Councel of State. And for their further incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, in caſe they ſhall ſink, fire, or by any other ways or means deſtroy the Admiral of the Revolted ſhips, or of any other Fleet that ſhall fight, or declare their intentions to fight or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Hoſtility againſt this Commonwealth, they ſhall receive of the State Twenty pounds <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> for each piece of Ordnance in ſuch Admiral ſo deſtroyed; and if the Vice-admiral, ſixteen pounds for each Gun; and if the Rere-admiral, twelve pounds <hi>Sterlin</hi> for each Gun; and if any other ſhip of War of the ſaid Revolted ſhips, or ſuch Fleet aforeſaid, Ten pounds for each Gun, to be diſtributed to the Captain, Officers and Mariners of the reſpective ſhips that ſhall be acting in the ſaid ſervice, and to be paid them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their wages: And alſo in caſe any of the States ſhips imployed in the ſervice of the Commonwealth, ſhall ſurprize or take any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſhips, either Engliſh or Strangers, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending in any of the caſes or particulars, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by this Act to be prize, and that the ſame ſhall be in the ſaid High Court of Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:119836:9"/> adjudged prize, according to the true meaning of this Act, That then after ſuch adjudication ſo given, the ſaid ſhips and goods ſo adjudged ſhall be ſold by the Candle, and the proceed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of divided into three equal parts; that is to ſay, One third part to be paid to the Captain or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptains, and other Officers and Mariners ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing or taking the ſame; and one other third part thereof to be diſpoſed of for the uſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, as the Parliament ſhall appoint; and the other third part thereof to be delivered into the Treaſurry before appointed, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of ſick and maimed Seamen, and the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, Children and Impotent Parents of the ſlain as aforeſaid. And further, in caſe any Merchant ſhip or ſhips, imployed in the ſervice of the State, ſhall take or ſurprize any Merchant ſhip as aforeſaid, Then the ſhip or ſhips ſo taken, being adjudged in the ſaid Court of Admiralty to be prize as aforeſaid, ſhall be ſold as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and the proceed thereof divided into three equal parts; that is to ſay, One third part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Captain or Captains, and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Mariners ſurprizing or taking the ſame; and one other third part thereof to be paid in to the Treaſury beforementioned, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed of to the uſe aforeſaid; and the other third part thereof to be equally divided into two parts; <hi>viz.</hi> One part thereof to the Owners of the ſaid ſhips; and the other part thereof to the State. And it is hereby Declared and Enacted, That ſuch ſhip or ſhips of the Fleet, that ſhall be in ſight or purſuit of the aforeſaid prize or prizes, when they ſhall happen to be ſo taken, and ſuch only ſhall have a proportionable ſhare in the ſaid prize or prizes, according to the Cuſtom of the Sea, Tun for Tun, and Man for Man.
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:119836:9"/> Provided always, That the Tenths of all prizes that ſhall be taken, cuſtomarily due to the Lord High Admiral, ſhall be paid in to the hands of ſuch Treaſurers as the Councel of State ſhall appoint for the profits of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty; the ſaid Tenths to be diſpoſed by order of the ſaid Councel of State, for meddals or other rewards, to ſuch Officers and Seamen of the Fleet, as by certificate under the hand and ſeal of the Commiſsioners commanding the Fleet at Sea, or any two of them, ſhall be found to have done any ſingular, eminent and extraordinory ſervice therein: And the ſaid Councel of State, is hereby required to take ſpecial care for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of this Act, in all points concerning the incouragement of Officers, Mariners and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to ingage in this ſervice, that none may be defrauded of any benefit or advantage, growing due unto them by vertue of this Act, or any thing therein contained, according to the tenor and true meaning thereof.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted, That if in any of the caſes aforeſaid, after ſentence definitive given in the ſaid Court of Admiralty, any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal ſhall be made from any ſuch ſentence, That then the parties appealing, ſhall within fifteen days after their appeal ſo made or interpoſed, ſue out their Commiſsion of delegacy under the Great Seal, and within two days after the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining thereof, preſent the ſame before two or more of the Iudges Delegates therein to be named, and procure from them not onely an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, but alſo a monition to the Regiſter of the Admiralty, to tranſmit the proceſs with all ſpeed; and ſhall alſo within ſix days after the preſentation of the ſaid Commiſsion, exhibit and give in their Libel appellatory, and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:119836:10"/> of appeal, that the ſame were interpoſed before any publique Notary, and proceed in the ſaid cauſes of appeal with effect, under the pain that the ſaid appeals be pronounced to be deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and remitted back to the Court of Admiralty. And for the more ſpeedy and effectual proceeding in the ſaid cauſes of appeal, and that right and juſtice may be duly therein adminiſtred, and yet no procraſtinations uſed, nor frivolous delays al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, Be it Enacted, That if no new matter ſhall within ſix days after the tranſmiſsion of the ſaid proceſs be pleaded, That then the Iudges of appeal ſhall proceed to conclude the cauſe, and aſsign the ſame for ſentence: And if any new matter ſhall be alledged, ſuch as ſhall be concludent and admiſsible by Law, That then the Iudges of appeal ſhall aſsign both parties ſome certain ſhort term, <hi>ad pro ponendum omnia que conſiſtunt in facto;</hi> and ſuch a competent time to make their proofs thereupon as ſhall be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, and ſo proceed to publication and concluſion of the cauſe, that the ſame may be finally ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced and adjudged according to the rights and merits of the caſe, without any other or farther ſtop or removal whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And as well the Iudges of the ſaid Court of Admiralty, as alſo the Iudges of appeal, are required and commanded to adminiſter Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice truly and indifferently, in all and every the caſes aforeſaid that ſhall reſpectively come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, according to the true intent and meaning of this Act, and according to the Civil Law, and Law of Nations, that no perſon may have juſt cauſe to complain either for delay or lack of juſtice. And be it further Enacted and Ordained, That the Councel of State ſhall be, and are hereby enabled by Warrant by
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:119836:10"/> them directed to the ſaid Court of Admiralty, to give licence to all ſuch well affected perſons as they ſhall approve of, to ſue out Commiſſions or Letters of Reprizal out of the ſaid Court, to enable them to ſet forth to Sea ſuch particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſhips, and private Men of War, under ſuch Captains and Officers as the Councel of State ſhall approve of, in Warlike maner, armed, equip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and furniſhed, for guard of the freedom of Trade, and ſafeguard of the Seas, and taking and ſurprizing of prizes in all and every the caſes particularly before recited in this Act, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame to judgement in the High Court of Admiralty; and having and converting the ſame to their own uſes, and the uſe of their Captains, Officers and Mariners ſurprizing the ſame, the tenths of all ſuch prizes, or the full and true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thereof firſt being duly paid to the State, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Cuſtoms and Excize likewiſe due and accuſtomed. Provided always, That there be firſt for every ſuch ſhip or private Men of War ſuing for ſuch Commiſsion, good ſecurity given in to the ſaid Court of Admiralty, not to preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice nor harm the Friends or Allies of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, nor any other perſon in any other caſes, then in the caſes declared in this Act to be prize; nor to pillage, ſpoil nor break bulk, before adjudication firſt paſſed in the ſaid Court of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty; and to tranſmit and ſend up thither, all the Papers, Writings and Demands that ſhall be found aboard the ſhips ſurprized, and to bring or procure, two or three, or more of every ſhip taken, to be duly examined, and to obſerve ſuch other inſtructions and conditions as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of State ſhall further direct. And to the end that due intimation and publication of this Act may be made, and publique notice thereof
<pb facs="tcp:119836:11"/> be taken, Be it Ordered and Enacted, That this preſent Act ſhall be publiſhed by a Sergeant at Arms, three ſeveral days upon the Exchange <hi>London,</hi> at the time of the concourſe of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants thither; and alſo copies thereof, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Clerk of the Parliament, to be ſent by the Speaker of the Parliament, to the Ambaſſadors and Miniſters of Foreign Nations here reſident, to be by them made known to the Subjects of thoſe Princes or States which they repreſent, or from whom they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <opener>
               <date>Die Martis, <hi>17</hi> Aprilis, <hi>1649.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That this Act be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen: Scobell, Cleric. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
